I'm going to talk about simulation in this
lecture.
Simulation is a very important topic, for
statistics and for a number of other
applications.
So, I just want to introduce some of the
functions in R that can be useful for
doing simulation.
So, there are a couple of functions that
are available for simulating, numbers or
variables from, given probability
distributions.
Probably the most important of which is
the Normal distribution.
And so, we can generate, variance from the
Normal distribution by specifying a mean
and a standard deviation for that
distribution, and then calling the rnorm
function.
So, the rnorm function will simulate
normal random variables, that from a
distribution that has a given mean and
standard deviation.
So the, there's a, there are corresponding
functions for the R, for the Normal
distribution that can be used to evaluate
the probability density, to evaluate the
cumulative distribution function, and for,
and also for evaluating the quantile
function.
So, another function for generating random
variables is the rpois function or the
which generates Poisson random variables,
from a Poisson distribution with a given
rate.
And so, the, so there are a number of
functions for generating random variables
from the, from the kind of the standard
probability distributions, and you can use
these, to do, to, to run simulations.
So, probability distribution functions,
there are basically four functions
associated with them.
And so, for any given distribution like
the Normal distribution, there will be a
function that starts with a d.
A function that starts with an r or the p
and a q.
So, it will be four different functions
for each distribution.
So, we've already, I've already mentioned
that there's the rnorm function.
So, the rnorm function is for generating
the, is for random number generation.
There's a dnorm function which evaluates
the density of the probability, distr-,
distribution for a given mean and standard
deviation.
There's the pnorm function, which
evaluates the cumulative distribution, and
there's the qnorm function, which
evaluates the quantile function.
So, every distribution has, these four
types of functions.
So, for the gamma distribution, there will
be a d gamma, an r gamma, a p gamma, and a
q gamma function.
And for the Poisson distribution, there's
the rpois, a dpois, a ppois, and qpois
functions.
So, working with the Normal distribution,
requires these four functions.
So, I mentioned the dnorm, pnorm, qnorm,
and rnorm and you can see that each take a
number of different parameters.
All of the functions required that you
specify the mean and the standard
deviation because that's what specifies
the actual probability distribution.
If you do not specify them and the default
values are a distribution, a standard
Normal distribution which has a mean zero
and standard deviation one.
For the dnorm function, the you, you can
evaluate the density, and there's an
optional, there's an option that allows
you to evaluate the log of the density.
Most of the time, when you evaluate the
density function for a Normal distribution
you're going to want to use the log of
that value.
But the default is false.
For the pnorm function and the qnorm
function, there's also an option to
evaluate it on a log scale.
But, but, but another option is to
evaluate the, is whether or not you want
to evaluate the lower tail of the
distribution.
So, the lower tail, which is the default,
is the, if you can think of it, if you
look at the probability distribution, it's
the part that goes to the left.
It's the lower tail.
If you wanted to evaluate the upper tail,
sometimes you want to do this.
Then you want to say, lower tail equals
false.
And that will evaluate the upper tail of
the distribution.
And finally for rnorm, there's, only two
parameters, mean and standard deviation.
And then N, which is number of random
variables that you want to generate.
So, if N is 100, you'll get a vector of
100 numbers that are drawn from the, from
the Normal distribution.
So, just to be more explicit, if phi is
the cumulative distribution function for
the standard normal distribution.
Then pnorm is equivalent to phi and qnorm
is equivalent to the inverse of phi.
So, just quickly, if you want to generate
some random normal, random normal
variants, you must call rnorm and pass an
integer, which is the number of variables
you want to generate.
So, here I'm passing ten.
And you can see that the vector that's
produced, will be random normal, numbers
which have mean zero and standard
deviation one.
If I want to generate a vector that had
mean twenty and standard deviation two, I
just need to specify that explicitly in my
call to rnorm.
So, here, this vector has a, is our ten
random normal bid, sorry normal random
variables, and their mean is roughly
twenty, and their standard deviation is
two.
So, when anytime you simulate random
numbers, with, from any distribution, for
any purpose.
It's very important that you set the
random number generator seed.
And this could be done with the set.seed
function.
So, what's important to know is that on
computers, when you generate random
numbers, the numbers are not actually
random.
But they appear random, and that's the
important thing.
And, if so the idea is that if you wanted
to generate the same set of random numbers
again, you could if you wanted to because
the numbers are not actually random.
They're called, they're, they're what are
called pseudo-random numbers.
And so, here I'm setting the seed to be
one.
So, the seed can be any integer you want.
You just pass it an integer and that's the
seed.
So, here I'm gonna set seed equal to one,
and then I'm gonna generate five random,
normal random variables.
And so here I've got my, my five normal
random variables.
They have mean zero and standard deviation
one.
If I generate another five, you'll see
that the vector is totally different
because it's another random sample of
five.
However, if I reset the seed to be one and
I draw five again.
You'll see that they are exactly the same
as the first five that I drew.
So anytime, so when you set the seed, it
kind of sets the sequence of random
variables that's just going to occur and
if you reset the seed you kind of set the
sequence to go back to where you started
and that it will continue to, kind of
generate random variables from there.
So, this is important because it allows
for you to reproduce random numbers that
you generate.
Now, that might sound strange because why
would you want to regenerate the same
random number twice.
But in many applications, you do want to
generate the same random numbers twice so
that people can reproduce what you've
done.
And in particular, if there are some
errors or problems in what you've done,
you want to be able to get just to kind
of, go back to the exact situation that
produced those problems.
So, whenever you do a simulation, you
always want to set the random number seed,
so that you can go back and get the same
results.
So, I've demonstrated how to generate
normal random variables.
But of course, you can generate, random
variables from other probability
distributions.
So, the Poisson distribution is of course
very popular.
Here, I'm generating a, ten poisson random
variables with a rate of one.
And, so, of course, Poisson data are going
to be integer.
Here, I'm generating a pois-, ten Poisson
random variables at the rate of two.
So, you can see they're slightly larger.
And then here, I'm generating a ten random
variables, Poisson random variables with
a, with a rate of twenty.
And so, so for the Poisson distribution,
the mean is gonna be equal to the rate.
So, you can see that, roughly, in each of
three cases, the mean is roughly equal to
the rate that I specified.
I could also evaluate the cumulative
distribution, function, for the Poisson
distribution.
So here, I'm.
In this first example, I want to know what
is the probability that, a Poisson random
variable is less than or equal to two if
the rate is two.
And so, this is the probability.
It's.67, roughly.
If I want to know what's the probability
that the, a Poisson random variable with
rate two is less than four, less than or
equal to four.
You can see the probability is getting
bigger.
And here, I can see the probability that a
Poisson random variable is less than six,
less than or equal to six.
And it's very close to one.
So, the cumulative distribution allows you
to, to evaluate these probabilities.
Now, we talked about how to simulate
random numbers from simple probability
distributions.
But the question now is how, what if you
want to, assimilate data from a, from a
model, for example like a linear model.
So, I've got a very simple linear model
here.
It has a single predictor x and it's going
to have random noise, what I call Epsilon,
that has a Normal distribution with
standard deviation two.
There's the, the outcome Is going to be
generated, by, by, by with using these two
regression coefficients about intercept
beta naught and a slow beta one.
I'm going to assume that beta naught is
equal to 0.5 and beta one is equal to two.
So, the question is how do I assimilate
from this model now that I specified what
it is.
So here, at first I set the seed.
Remember it's always very important to set
that seed.
So, I set it to twenty.
I generate x, the predictor which has a
standard normal distribution.
I generate epsilon which is going to have
a standard, a normal distribution with
mean zero and standard deviation two.
And then, I'm going to add them altogether
by, and after multiplying the regression
coefficient to generate my y.
And so, from the summary here, you'll see
that y has roughly the mean of .68.
And it ha-, it ranges from about minus six
to plus six.
And then I can plot the data to see what
they look like, and here they are on the
next slide.
So this is the plot of the x that I
simulated, and the y that I simulated from
the linear model.
And you can see that they very clearly
have a linear relationship, according,
that follows the model that we specified.
So, just a slight variation of the
previous example, What if x is a, instead
of x being a normal random variable, what
if X is a binary random variable.
So, maybe it represents, gender or maybe
it's some treatment versus control or
something like that.
So, here this is very simple.
I can generate binary data using the
binomial distribution, and the r binome
function.
So, I set the seed again, and I generate,
100 binomial random variables, and these
are going to have, this is from, this
comes from the binomial distribution which
is N equal to one and P equal to half.
So, the probability of one is gonna be
equal to .5.
So, I generate 100 of those.
And then I generate my normal random
variables.
My normal error term, which is going to be
mean, be mean zero, and standard deviation
two.
And then I add them all together to
produce my y.
So now, when I look at the summary of y, I
see the mean is about 1.4 and a range is
from about minus three to six or seven.
So when I, now when I plot the data, of
course they'll look very different because
the x variable is binary.
But the y variable is still continuous,
it's normal.
So here, you can see that there's, there
appears to be a pretty clear, again,
linear trend when x, between going from x
equal to zero and x is equal to one.
Now, suppose you want to simulate from a
slightly more complicated model a, a
generalized linear model, perhaps with a
Poisson distribution.
And so, for example, you might want to
simulate some outcome data that have, that
are count variables instead of continuous
variables.
So, we have to use, use a slightly more
complicated approach to do this
particular, because the error distribution
is not going to be normal.
It's going to be a Poisson distribution.
And so, let's assume that the outcome y
has a Poisson distribution with mean mu,
and, and the log of mu follows a linear
model with a intercept, beta naught and
the a slope beta one.
So, x is going to be one of our
predictors.
So, let's assume that beta naught is .5,
and beta one is .3.
So, how do we simulate from this model, to
get our Poisson data?
So, so we need to use the rpois function
for this.
And so, we first set the seed as always.
And we generate our predictor variable, x,
which is going to have a standard normal
distribution.
Then we're going to simulate, generate our
lin-, linear predictor, log of mu.
Which is just adding the slope and, and
the, the intercept and the slope
coefficient times x.
So, that's the log of our linear
predictor.
But when, in order to get the mean for our
Poisson random variable, we need to
exponentiate that.
So we, we simulate a hundred of these,
Poisson random variables, using the rpois
function, and we give it the ex-,
exponential of our log mean.
So when we, summarize this, you'll see
that the mean is about, 1.5.
And it ranges between zero and six.
When I plot this data, you'll see that,
they look like Poisson data.
And that there's clearly a linear
relationship between x and y.
As x increases the count for y generally
gets larger.
But the data are still account variables
here.
So, last function I want to talk about, is
the sample function.
And the way, and the sample function
allows you to draw randomly from a
specific set of objects, that you specify.
So, if you give it a vector of numbers, it
allows to draw a random sample from that
vector of numbers.
And so you can kind of create any
arbitrary distribution that you want by
specifying a vector of objects and then
sampling from it.
So here, for example, I'm going to sample
from the integers one to ten.
So, I pass it the vector of integers one
through ten.
And I tell it that I wanna sample randomly
four of them without replacement.
So, so, I'm just choosing four random
entries from one to ten.
And here, I get three, four, five, seven.
If I do it again, I'll get, three, nine,
eight, five.
So, in this example, I, I won't, I won't
get repeated numbers, because I'm not
sampling with replacement.
I don't have to just sample numbers.
I could sample letters if I wanted to.
So here, I'm taking the letters a through
z.
And I was going to sample five of them
without replacement.
And I just get q, b, e, x, and p.
Now, what happens if I don't specify
anything?
I just give it the vector of objects.
So here, as passing sample, the vector one
through.
Ten.
And if I don't specify anything else, what
it does is it gives me a permutation of
those.
So, here the vector, one through ten is
just permutted in a random order.
If I call it again, I get a, I get yet
again permutation.
So, lastly I want to sample from one
through ten, but with replacement, I can
specify the replacement equals true
argument.
So now, I'm sampling one through ten.
I'm getting a vector of ten numbers from
the vector one through ten, but because
it's with replacement, I can get repeat.
So, you can see I got eight, three times,
and I got nine, multiple times.
So, that's how you sample with the
placement.
So, that's a very quick summary of the
simulation functions in R.
You can draw random samples from specific
probability distributions, with the R
functions.
So, rnorm, R plus.
Or sorry, rpois, rbinom that we saw
already.
All the standard distributions are going
to be built in that you have, probably,
you will need.
Things like normal, the Poisson, the
binomial, the exponential gamma, etcetera.
All those functions are built in.
And you can use the corresponding R
functions, to simulate from them.
The sample function can be used to draw,
random samples from arbitrary vectors.
So, if you want to kind of create your own
distribution here.
And then.
It's very important to, to remember to set
the random number generator seed any time
you simulate data in R, so that you can
reproduce the results that you got.
At a later date.