In addition to the base plotting system,
the other main mode of plotting for R is
the lattice, is through the lattice
package.
Remember we call it the lattice package.
It uses the grid package, to create a
different style of plot from the standard
base package.
And the main difference between lattice
and base is that the lattice functions
generally create plots all in one go
rather than, kind of, creating a, the, the
foundation of a plot, and then adding
points or adding texts or adding
annotations, or things like that.
Most of the functions in lattice will try
to make construct the entire plot from a
single function call.
So, the main functions, in the lattice
package are the xyplot for creating
scatter plots.
Bwplot for creating, what I called
box-and-whisker plots, or just boxplots.
Histogram for creating histograms.
Stripplot, it's kind of like a boxplot but
with, but with points instead of the
boxes.
Dotplot.
Splom, which stands for scatterplot
matrix.
It is analogous to the pairs function in
the base graphic system.
And then levelplot and contourplot are for
plotting, image data.
The basic, approach of lattice functions
is that the first argument is usually a
formula of some sort.
And the formula can look something like
this.
So here, I've got y tilde x.
So, you can think of y as being the
response of some sort.
So, it's gonna be on the y axis.
X is the input, or so to speak.
It's gonna be on the x axis.
And then the solidus, it represents
conditioning on, f and g.
And f and g are typically going to be
factors.
So, here we've got two different factors
that are interacting with each other.
There won't, won't always be two different
factors, often there will just be one.
But the idea is that, the are the strength
of the lattice functions is that you can
plot, conditional relationships, where you
condition on the relationship say between
x and y based on a third factor variable.
So, for example f might represent, a
level, a factor variable categorizing men
and women and you might now look at the,
relationship between x and y for both men
and women separately.
So, So that.
So, so the lattice function is very useful
for that kind of, for plotting that kind
of data.
And then, so the lattice functions will
usually take a data frame as a second
argument where the variables y, x, f and g
will be looked up to, to find their
values.
If there's no data frame pass then it will
look into the parent frame to see.
To find the values of those variables.
So, lattice functions behave differently
from base graphics functions in a, in a
very critical but subtle way.
So, the idea with base graphics functions
is that they plot data directly onto the
graphics device.
In more formal language it's, this is
called having a side effect.
So, all of the base graphics functions
have a side effect, which is that they
plot, data to the graphics device.
Lattice graphics functions are a little
bit different because rather than plot
something to the graphics device.
What they do is they return object of
class trellis.
And so, they don't actually plot anything
particularly.
All they do is they create an object that
is designed for plotting and they return
it to you and that object has a special
class.
It's called trellis.
And then what happens is that when you
print that object, the print method does
the work of plotting the data to the
graphics device.
So, and so when you call that as function,
what happens is that even if you don't
assign it to an object, the result of that
lattice will be auto-printed.
And so, the auto printing will generate
the graphics onto, the, the plot on the
graphics device.
So, it will look like things are just
being plotted and that the lattice
functions have a side effect.
But rather, the returned object is going
to, is, is auto-printed, to the graphics
device.
Now in theory, that, what this means is
that you, you can kinda save the object
that's returned by the lattice function
and, and maybe save it to a file or
something like that.
But usually that's not a very good, a very
good idea.
It's usually better just to save the code
that created the, the object, and the data
that are inputted.
Lattice functions also have a critical
feature called a panel function.
And so, when you condition on, a factor
variable in a formula, there's gonna be a
separate panel created for each level of
the factor.
So for example, if you're conditioning on
a factor variable that, that, that encodes
gender, and it has two levels, male and
female, then what's going to happen is
that you're going to have a, a plot that
has two pa-, two panels.
One panel for males, another panel for
females.
And the panel function controls what
happens inside each of these panels for
the entire plot.
So, here I'm simulating some data, some
normal data that have a linear
relationship, and I'm going to create a
factor variable, that has two groups
labeled Group one and Group two.
So, ` if I call xy plot for y tilde x and
then condition on f, you, this is the plot
that you get.
So, you can see that there are two panels,
Group one, one for Group one and one for
Group two.
And, and, and all that happens within each
panel is that a scatterplot is created.
Now, I can modify my plot by adding a
custom panel function.
So, that, so in the process, plot I just
use the default panel function.
But, I can create my own panel function,
by writing this little anonymous function
here, and the first two arguments are
going to be x and y.
So, you can think, tho-, those are the x
coordinates and the y coordinates of the
points that are going to be plotted in a
specific panel.
So, it's not the, it's not all the data
that you pass to the xy plot function,
it's just the data that appear in a given
panel.
And so, what I'm going to do for, in, in
my custom panel function, is I'm going to
call the panel dot xy plot function to
just plot the data points and use all the
default options.
So, all the default options are getting
passed through the dot, dot, dot argument.
But I just want to do, I want to add one
extra thing, which is that I wanto add, I
want to plot the median of the y values in
each panel.
So, here I'm using panel.ab line, and I'm
saying, and I'm calculating the median of
y and I'm going to specify a line type of
two.
So, here I'm going to, I'm going to plot,
within each panel, I'm going to plot the
median of y, in that panel, and it's gonna
be a dashed line.
So, so, here you can see that I've used
these two functions, panel.xyplot and
panel.abline.
You might recall that there's another
function just called abline, which is used
in the base graphics system.
But you cannot use functions from the base
plotting system, in a Lattice plot.
So, lattice, for better or for worse has
duplicated many of those types of
functions, in its own version.
So, you have to call the panel.abline
function instead of just the abline
function.
In the previous plot, I just added a
horizontal line for the median of y, but
suppose I wanted to add a regression line
for each of the panels in my plot.
So now I can, I can call my custom for
panel function after plotting the points
with the panel.xyplot function.
I can call the panel.lmline function, and
here I was supposed to find that I want
the regression line to be of colors equals
too, which is, which is going to be, red.
So, here the panellmline function just
adds an regression line to each of the
panels.