One nice feature of R is the ability to do
mathematical annotation within the
plotting device.
So you can make plots that have
mathematical symbols in them to annotate
them and provide context.
So if you're familiar with the, the
language with the typesetting system known
as LaTeX then your ability, then your
ability, then you have the ability to
produce LaTeX like symbols on the plot
for, for, for doing mathematical
annotation.
So this is very useful if you want to make
fun of other people who use other
statistical packages cuz they, generally
speaking, don't have the ability to add
LaTeX like symbols onto their plots.
So if you're, if you want to make a plot
that's a lot nerdier than those plots then
this is the way to do it.
So, the basic idea is that math symbols
are expressions in r.
And so you have to use the expression
function to encode them when you're using
them in a plot.
So there's a list, there's a list, a
specific list of a, of allowed symbols
for, for plotting mathematical annotation,
and they're documented in the help page
for plot math.
And so the, if you're interested in doing
this kind of annotation, you should really
look at the help page for plot math, and,
and basically have it memorized, cuz it's
not that very long, and they're are not
that many symbols.
So you can have it, in your head, and then
do all ca, all the mathematical annotation
that you want.
So plotting, plotting functions that take
arguments for any, for text, so like the
title function the axis function the text
function, all these functions that take
arguments that put labels on the plot,
will g, will generally allow expressions
for the math symbol.
So, while you can pass regular text to be
plotted on the, on the, on the graphics
device, you can also pass in an expression
that will be translated into a
mathematical annotation.
So here's a simple example.
Here, I'm just plotting I'm not plotting
any data but I'm creating, I'm setting up
a plot window where the title of the plot
is going to be the, the expression theta
equal zero.
The y label is going to be expression,
gamma hat equal zero.
And the x label is going to be the sum, so
like, so you can think ofs, the capital
sigma representing the sum, where I goes
from one to n of xi times yi, the product
xi times yi.
So these expressions will appear in the
plot window and, and will be typeset in a
LaTeX like manner.
You can also paste strings together so,
if, so for example, here, I can creating a
histogram where the x label, as the
expression the mean, and then in
parenthesis, x bar, is, and then the sum,
you know, x, xi over n from i, you, it
goes from one to n.
So here, it's just defining what x bar is,
which is the mean.
So you can paste strings together like
this which include, you know, standard
text plus mathematical expressions.
However, when you do this, all of it must
occur within the expression function.
So one question is, so in the previous
example, I put hard coded, just constants,
into the In to the labels that I want to
plot on, in the graphics device.
What happens if the expression that you
want to plot is actually the result of a
computation?
For example, suppose you want to say that
the mean x bar is equal to and then the,
and then the mean of your data.
Well you're not going to know what the
mean of your data is until you calculate
it and so you might want to put the actual
calculation of the mean into the
expression itself.
So here I'm generating some data to have a
linear relationship, x and y, and I want
to plot x and y and on the, on the x axis,
I want to have the x label be the mean of
x.
And on the y axis, I want to have the x,
the y label be the mean of y.
So, of course, I don't know what those
numbers are until I calculate them, so I'm
going to use the substitute function to
pa, rather than the expression function,
because the substitute function will
substitute the actual value of the mean
into my plot.
So here I'm saying that bar of x, which is
x, which is so is going to be x bar, is
equal to k.
And then and for k, I say I have, I passed
the list k is equal to the mean of x.
And similarly for, for the y label I say
bar y or x bar equal to k, where in this
case k is equal to the mean of y.
So now what substitute's going to do is
going to, is going to take the, it's going
to take k, it's going to, it's going to
substitute in the actual value of the mean
of x for the x label and then the mean of
y for the y label.
And so when I'm plo, when I call this plot
and direct it toward the plot window where
na on, on my y label and my x label I am
going to have the mean of each of those
dimensions.
So ya, and this, the example down here,
I've got four plots and I'm trying to make
two, in a two by two matrix.
And I've got an old four loop here that's
making the plots, and what I'm going to do
is I'm going to create a histogram of some
random genera, randomly generated data,
and in each and each histogram I want to
put the title to be theta equals a number
one, two, three, four.
So here I'm just substituting I'm saying,
I'm using the substitute, I'm saying theta
equals num, and then num is going to be
equal to i, which is the index and the
four loop, which is going to be one, two,
three and four.
So you can see the result here, is that I
get four plots, and the title for each one
is theta is equal to one, two, three or
four.
So, this is just some of the mathematical
annotation that you can do in R.
You can get a lot fancier if you want to.
So, and in looking at the plot math help
page will allow you to see what kinds of
symbols you can put into your plots.
So, just a very quick summary of the
important health pages that are useful to
know when you're doing plotting in R.
The par function definitely should be
looked at to look at all the different
options that you can specify when in the
base plotting system.
The plot function, of course, is quite
useful.
In the lattice system the xy plot function
it has pretty much all of the help
information that you're going to need if
you use the lattice system.
The plot malt hea, math help page is
useful for if you're doing mathematical
annotation and it is actually relevant to
both the base plotting and the lattice
plotting system.
So you can do mathematical annotation in
both systems using the same approach.
And finally the axis function it's
actually quite useful if you, for the base
plotting system if you want to annotate
axis in special ways.