In this video I want to talk a little bit
about using the Lattice package in R.
The way that you use the Lattice package
is a little bit different from, say, the
base plotting functions that you use in
the base plotting system.
And so I want to talk a little bit about
how you kind of write the code to make the
plots that you want to use.
So, when using the Lattice package, it's
often useful to have a separate editor
open to write code, because the, the
function calls to the Lattice function
tend to be a little bit more involved, and
it's hard to fit them all, or it's a
little inconvenient to fit them all into a
single line.
In the base graphic system, a lot of times
you're, you're calling single functions,
and you're calling a whole bunch of
functions to make a single plot.
In the, the lattice package you are just
usually calling one or maybe two
functions, and the, and the one function
call will set up, although, an entire
plot, so often you'll have a really long
function call.
And it's easier to have an editor window
open to write all that code.
Here I'm using R Studio, and in the upper
left I've got the editor window.
And in the bottom left here I've got the
console.
Other, other programs are fine for using a
text editor if you want, if you want to
use the standard R console.
But R Studio is actually quite helpful for
this kind of thing.
So the first thing you can do is load the
library, the lattice package like this in
the usual way.
Excuse me, and if you want to take a look
at some general information about lattice
say package lattice, package question mark
lattice, that is.
And at least in our studio over here
you'll see a nice little description of
the lattice package, with some general
information.
Some references and some links to all of
the functions in the lattice package that
you may want to look at.
The most important function in the lattice
package really is the XY plot function so
I'll click on that here.
And the XY plot function gives you a long
list of arguments and options that can be
passed to the function and a description
of all those arguments.
So I'm going to move on and start plotting
some data.
So the first thing we're gonna do is we're
gonna see what's in the lattice package
here.
And you can see that there are number of
functions and data sets available here.
And the one data set we're going to look
at is the environmental data set here.
So I'm going to load that data set for us
to use here.
So, I'm loading the environmental data
set.
And, of course, you can always get the
help page for each data set.
So I can take a look at that here.
And you can see it's environmental,
conditions in New York City in 197-,
September.
Sorry, excuse me.
May to September of 1973.
You have information about ozone,
radiation, temperature and, wind.
So, and, and, of course, there's, other
variables for the dates.
So, we've loaded this data set here.
So let's just take a look at the first
couple of rows here.
You can see down at the console here the
ozone radiation temperature and wind
variables.
And so I'm going to simple, make a simple
scatter plot of ozone and radiation.
So the way you do this is with the XY plot
function, and it's backwards from the
usual plotting function.
So instead of doing X and Y, you're going
to do Y tilt to X.
So on the Y axis I want ozone, and on the
X axis I want radiation.
So I'm going to do that, do it this way
here.
So it's kind of like a response and a
predictor.
And then you also have to give it a data
argument, which tells the function xy plot
where to find the variables ozone and
radiation.
Because ozone and radiation are not
objects in my work space.
They are variables in this data frame.
So what xy plot will do, is it'll look up
those, names inside this data frame.
Close that, and you can see that the
function is called, and plot appears in
the right, here.
And, looks like a standard scatter plot,
nothing, may be slightly different from
the usual plotting function.
I can see that, actually a lot of the,
spacing has been arranged for you, so that
the plot goes more or less to the edges,
it doesn't waste any space on the edges.
You have to set any spacing options, so I
could have done some thing like xy plot
and then add a little title to it.
So maybe I'll say main equals ozone,
versus radiation.
And if I run that, you'll see that the
plot is made, but the title is added to
the top.
And notice that the, that the, the
plotting region was squished down just a
tiny little bit, so that the title could
be, fit into there.
But just, only enough room was made to
create the title so as to not waste any
space.
Okay.
So, there's another variable here which is
temperature.
So I could plot temperature here.
And this is what it looks like here.
So nothing special.
But of course one of the things that,
that, that the lattice package function
excels at is allowing you to plot, kind of
multivariate, or lattice, type plots, so,
which allow you to look at the
relationships between variables, when you
condition on the levels of another
variable.
So for example, on this plot up here, we
will look at ozone and radiation.
One of the questions you might want to
know is whether or not the relationship
between ozone and radiation changes as the
temperature changes.
So first thing you'll notice in this plot
is that there's kind of a cone shape to
it, and as the radiation increases the,
the variability in ozone seems to
increase.
So one thing that maybe, one thing that
maybe going on here is that there's an
interaction with the third variable, maybe
temperature which modifies the
relationship between ozone and radiation
in the background.
And so we can plot the relationship
between ozone and radiation for different
values of the temperature variable to see
if that rela-, relationship is changing
with temperature.
So the first, that's, so temperature
continuous variable, as you'll see here,
so you can't exactly condition on the
levels of temperature, because there are
theoretically infinite number of levels of
temperature.
So, what we're going to want to do is cut
the temperature variable into a few
different, ranges.
And then we'll plot the ozone and
radiation relationship within those ranges
of temperature.
So I'm going to create a, another variable
here, called Temp, Cut, which is going to
be the, I'm going to use the equal count
function on the original temperature
variable.
And I'm going to give, what I'm going to
do is I'm going to create four different
ranges of the temperature, of the original
temperature variable, so that I can use
this in my plotting.
So when I call this, and I print out the
new variable, you'll see that what it does
is create, it creates what is called a
shingle variable, and the shingles here
are, are different intervals that are
slightly overlapping.
So you see the first interval goes from
56.5 to 76.5 degrees Fahrenheit.
And there are 46 observations in that
range and in the next shingle goes from
67.5 to 81.5, there's 51 observations in
that range.
And you can see that in the first range
and the second range overlap just a little
bit and then in the third range which
overlaps with the second it's 75.5 to 86.5
degrees Fahrenheit.
Again there's 51 observations.
And then the last shingle also has 51
observations.
So this function created four ranges of
the temperature variable, all of which
overlap slightly.
And, and have equal, roughly equal numbers
of observations in them.
So now what we're going to do up at the
top here, so I'm going to plot the ozone
and radiation data, but I'm going to
condition on the ranges of this temp
variable.
Okay.
And so know what it-, you'll see is now
I've created a lattice plot here, where
each of the four plot, there, of the four
plots here, plots ozone versus radiation,
but for a different range of temperatures.
So on the bottom left over here, this is
the rel-, this, these are, there is 46
observations here.
I'm looking at ozone and temp-, and
radiation for the kind of range of
temperature that's between 56.5 and 76.5
degrees Fahrenheit.
And you can see, actually that's there
almost no relationship between ozone and
radiation, in this temperature ring.
This is a fairly cool, temperature range.
So one thing that's, that we know about
ozone is that, it's, the, the production
of ozone is related to the temperature.
So, the warmer the temperature, the more
ozone you're going to get in the
atmosphere.
So perhaps we should expect that in the
cooler range of temperature, we're not
gonna see much of a relationship between
radiation and ozone.
As to now, in the second range here, we
see, that, that there is a, not much of a
relationship between ozone temperatures,
though there are a few outliers here.
And then as you increase the temperature
in the third plot here of an, on the upper
left, you see that there's a, there's an
increasing relationship with radiation.
And then, in the fourth plot here, you
see.
Even more of a relationship between ozone
and radiation for the last temperature
range, which is between 80.5 and 97.5
degrees Fahrenheit.
And so the, the, the x, y plot function is
useful for making these kind of
conditioning plots.
Where we plot the relationship between two
variables.
And by con-, and condition on the levels
of a third variable.
In this case, the temperature variable
which we've cut into four different
ranges.
There are a few other things that we can
do to this plot just to make, re-arrange
it a little bit, just in case you don't
like the default layout.
For example we can we can change the
order, arrangement of the plot so if the
default arrangement goes from the bottom
left to the bottom right to the top left
to the top right.
If you don't like that, you can, you can
change it, so that, for example, we can
have four on top each other.
So we can say layout is one, four, and
then when we do this.
So you'll see there are four different
plots, all on top of each other and now
you can see perhaps a little bit more
clearly, that the ranges of the
temperature are overlapping slightly.
And, and exact roughly speaking kind of
where, how they relate to each other.
We can also change the order in which the
plots are drawn, so instead of say for
example from bottom to top, which is the
default, we can draw the plots from top to
bottom by simply adding the as.table
argument, saying as.table equals true and
that will give us the, the reverse order.
So now you can see that the, the plot for
the bottom temperature range is on the
plot, is on the top, and the temperature
increases as you go down.
You can do this also without the, if you
wanted the, if you liked the original
layout with the four plots as in a square,
you can do that, and now you can see that
the, the plot goes from the top left down
to the bottom right.
Another thing that might be useful to do
for visualization purposes is to actually
plot the relationship between solar
radiation and ozone within each of the
panels.
And the way we can do this is to write our
own panel function here.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to
edit this call here, and I'm going to add
a, my own panel function here so and I'm
just going to do.
So the typical panel function has x for
the x coordinates, and y for the y
coordinates, so you can think of these as
the x and the y coordinates for each
panel.
So the same function is going to be
applied to each panel.
And so it has to work for the data in each
of the four panels.
And then the dot, dot, dot argument is all
of the other graphics parameters that
would normally be passed to the default
panel function, which I'm not going to
modify at all.
So now I've got my, I'm going to write my
custom panel function.
And the first thing I'm going to do is
call the default panel function.
And the reason why is I want to be able to
set up a plotting region, I want to be
able to set the plot symbol, the colors,
the labels, everything.
None of that is something I want to
change, all I want to do is add a
regression line to the plot.
So now I've got my plot set up.
I can fit a simple linear regression
model, which is using the LM function of Y
tilde X and then I can add the line.
To the plot with the panel.ad line
function.
And just give it the fit, output from LM,
and that's it.
So that's my custom, panel function here.
So now, I'm going to call, I'm going to
run this whole block of code.
Excuse me, and when I do you, will see
that in each of the panels a regression
line is overlaid on to the data which is
the, kind of regression fit to the data
within that panel.
And as you can see, the regression line is
relatively flat in the upper left panel.
And as you go to the upper right to the
lower left and then to the lower right the
slope of the line is increasing as you go
along.
You can use some of the standard plotting,
options if you want to modify the, the,
the plotting, in the, within each panel.
For example, if you wanted to make the
line a little bit thicker, you can say LWD
is equal to two.
And maybe, let's say you wanted to change
the plotting symbol to be a solid circle,
so I can just in the call to x, y plot, to
see if PC is equal to twenty.
That will give me a solid circle.
So now I'm going to run this code.
You'll see that the plotting symbol has
changed, and the regression line's a
little bit thicker.
And so you can modify this to, until it
looks the way you want it to look.
You can see why you might want to use the
text editor now when you're using the
lattice package.
Because the function calls to things like
xy plot, to, can get very quickly
complicated, just because you're
customizing things, and you're adding your
own panel function and whatever.
All of it under the same function call.
So I'm just going to add, maybe just, one
modification here.
Instead of doing a linear model, I'm going
to use a low s, which is just a smoother.
So I can do, panel, excuse me.
Panel low e-, panel low s here.
On xy, and that will get me a smooth
rendition of the line.
So now you can see that actually, the, in
the lower right, which is the high
temperature range, the relationship
appears to be a little bit non linear
there, which an increase, with, with
radiation, but then a decrease at the very
end.
I can, also just change the labels on the
X axis, and maybe on the X lab I want to
say, solar radiation, and then on the Y
label.
I just want to say ozone, maybe in part
per billion.
So I can run this code now.
Oh I, let me just add a title.
And I can put this on the next line here.
So now I can run this code again.
And you can see that the margins and
everything gets adjusted.
So you're able to fit the, the labels onto
the plot.
And so you don't have to worry about
things like spacing.
Finally, I just want to show one more
example of how you can look at
interactions in R.
So I, so there's a, there's one more
variable in this data set, which is the
wind variable.
And so we can look at how ozone and solar
radiation vary with both temperature and
wind.
So I'm going to cut the wind variable
into, again, four parts, with the equal
count function.
You can see that we can just take a look
at the, this new variable here, and you
can see that there are four intervals and
they do overlap, but and they're roughly
equal count within each interval.
So now I can, I'm going to take my
original code here, paste it in, but now
I'm going to, I'm gong to plot the
relationship by range of temperature and
by range of wind.
And so we can run this code now and see
what happens.
And so now you can see that actually
there's sixteen plots now instead of four,
which makes sense, because there's four
different levels of temperature and
there's four different levels of wind, so
the combination of the, of the two
together is sixteen possible combinations.
So you can see on the on the upper left
here is for when wind and temperature are
on the low range, and all the way down
here at the bottom right is when wind and
temperature are in their high range, and
everything else in between is for some
combination of wind and temperature in
between.
So you can see that these, you can see how
the relationship between solar radiation
and ozone changes for different
combinations of low wind/high temperature,
low temperature/high wind etc.
Or maybe medium wind and medium
temperature, and you can see that the
relationship is perhaps most interesting
with, for the kind of high temperature,
and then maybe low to moderate wind, and
then in this upper right corner over here
you can see the positioning on the
relationship there between the radiation
and the ozone.
And so you can see that for each of the
two conditioning variables there's a
little highlight slider that shows kind of
where you are on either the wind or the
temperature range, whether you're low, in
the middle, or you're in the high end and,
so that helps you kind of see where you
are in the range of the conditioning
variable.
So, these things can all be kind of
customized if you want in terms of the
colors and the labeling, but this, but by
default you can see that the, that R, the
X Y plot function will use the name of the
variable as the label within the strip up
here.
So that's a quick demo of the X Y plot
function in lattice.
There are a few other handy functions in
the lattice package that of course your,
you can use and may find handy.
So one of them is the scatter plot matrix
function or the SPLOM function.
So you can use the, the SPLOM function to
look at pairwise relationships, so I'm
going to use SPLOM, and then you give it a
tilde and then give it, you can give it
the entire data set.
If you want to look at all possible
combinations in this data set and when you
run that you'll see it makes those scatter
plots of all the different variables
against each other in, in to each one
plotted in two different forms.
You can also look at histograms with the
histogram function.
So you can look at histogram of, let's say
a single variable, say temperature, and
give a data equals environmental here.
And with that right, you will see a
histogram of the temperature variable
here.
So that's pretty standard.
There's nothing particularly special about
that.
But again, you could look at something
like temperature at the, histogram,
histogram of temperature as the wind
varies, so I can say, I can use my
wind.cut variable and then plot a
histogram of temperature for each range of
wind, and you can see that the
distribution of temperature doesn't change
too dramatically as the wind changes.
But another thing we could do is say look
at the histogram of O, the distribution of
ozone as the wind changes, and see if that
is of anything, is anything interesting.
And you can see that as the, as the wind
increases, the ozone is a little bit more
concentrated in the lower range.
Whereas, when there's very little wind,
the distribution seems to be spread a
little bit, to, towards the higher range.
So the distribution does appear to change
a little bit, with wind.
So, so that's the histogram function,
which can be used in, in very much the
same way as the ozone func-, as the xy
plot function, excuse me.
Where you can condition on different
variables.
Of course, we could condition on both
temperature and wind, to see what the
distribution looks like when you condition
on those two variables.
And you can see that, as wind and
temperature changes, the distribution does
become more spread out, or more
concentrated towards zero, depending on
which way you're going.
So in the bottom right over here we see
that when there is very low wind and very
high temperature, the distribution is
most, kind of spread out towards the
higher range whereas when there is very
high temperature and very low wind, excuse
me, when there is very high wind and very
low temperature in the upper left, most of
the values of ozone are concentrated
around zero.
So that's the histogram and scatter plot
matrix function and as well as the X Y
plot function.
So these are just a few of the functions
in the lattice package that can be used to
plot data, and then more importantly to
plot conditional relationships of data in
a way that's very compact and very useful
to visualize.