So here, I've started up bar and I'm just
gonna do a little bit of simple plotting
to just kind of show what the, the basics
are of the of the, the plotting options.
So, I'm going to stimulate a litte, a
little bit of data here so I can make a
plot.
So, I have a hundred random variables here
and I'm going to call it hist to make
histogram of the plot.
So, the first thing you'll, you'll notice
when I called hist, is that a plot window
opens up.
So, let me just move it over here, and the
histogram of the data is shown.
And you can see that, even though I didn't
actually specify any arguments to hist
besides the data themselves a number of
things appeared on the plot ag, without my
specifying them.
So, for example, there's a title here and
then there's an x label here, so here the,
the label is just x because that's what
the object was called when I passed it to
hist.
The label here is frequency which is the
default for histogram so it shows you the
number of elements within this range.
So, for example, between minus one and
zero there's going to, there's a little
over 30 elements of the vector in that
range and you can see that the shape of
the histogram is roughly like a normal
distribution.
So, let me just generate some more data
here and so, we can make a little scatter
plot.
So, I'm going to generate some more data
and I'll plot xy here.
So now, the plotting window is already
open, so when I call plot it's not going
to launch a new plotting window, it's
going to send the plot to the, the current
plotting window, which is this one here.
So, I've specified, I've called plot and
you can see the mixed scatter plot of the
points the default plotting symbol here is
an open circle you can see and again the
labeling, I didn't specify any arguments
besides x and y, but the number of things
have occurred in the plot, for example,
the label here as specified as x on the
x-axis and the label on the y-axis is
specified as y.
If I had changed the name of the object,
so let's say, I say rnorm 100 here and I
plot x and z.
Well, the plot looks different because the
data are different but you can see the
label here turn, turn to z, because that's
the name of the object.
So, let me just go back to x and y.
And so, a number of things on the plotting
region are important for example, the
margins here are, are these are four
margins here, one for each side.
This is side one, this is side two this is
side three and this is side four over
here.
You can see the margin for the bottom is,
is, is the largest.
So, there's, there's five lines of margin
text available.
On the side two, there's four lines of
margin text available.
On the top, there's also four, so side
three, and on the right side, side four,
there's the smallest amount of a margin
text available.
So, you can adjust that using the mar
function.
So, for example, I can just say par, and
then I say mar equals, let's say, I want,
let's say, I want two on every side.
So, two, two, two, two.
Excuse me.
And then I can plot again and you can see
that now the plot the margins have gotten
a lot smaller and the plot kind of extends
farther out into the window.
But the problem, as you can see that on
the x and the y-axis, I lost my label.
And so, even though I have the tick marks
there I don't have my x and y label.
So, we probably need to make them a little
bigger than that.
So, maybe I'll say four, four, two, two,
like that.
So now, if I plot again now you can see
there is just enough for the x and y label
there.
I'm just going to demo a couple of the
other options that may be of interest to
you as you're quick constructing your
plot.
So, the first is the plotting symbol.
I can say plot xy and then pch equals,
let's say, twenty.
That gives me a solid circle here.
If I want a slightly solid symbol here I
could say pch = nineteen.
Or I could, you know, specify pch = two
and that gives me triangles, three gives
me little plus signs, four gives me xs,
etc.
As you can see, so, you can see that
there's many different plotting symbols to
try.
You might be wondering how I know all the
numbers for these plotting symbols.
Well, that just comes after many years of
use, I've memorized most of them all but
of course, if you haven't memorized them
quite yet a handy tool is the example file
for points.
So, if you just hit points, example set of
points it'll go through a number of demos
so you can see how the capabilities that R
that R can do of plotting.
But most important are the, is there a
little plot of, sorry, a little chart of
the symbols here.
And so, you can see that's a, for example,
one is a open circle, two is the triangle,
three is the plus, etc.
Here twenty was the solid circle, small,
nineteen, was the larger circle.
If you wanted a solid square, that's
fifteen a solid triangle of seventeen,
etc.
So, you can specify what type of symbol
you want just by using the number here.
Another, the thing, if you notice the
symbols 21 through 25 those are actually
symbols that are similar to say, to ones
that are, that have been previously shown,
so for example, one through six.
However, the difference is in 21 through
25, those symbols have a have a boundary
so you can see that the boundary is red.
And they have a fill which in this case is
yellow.
So, you can specify two different colors,
one for the boundary and for the outline,
and one for the color.
And so, the boundary color is specified
using the col, col argument.
And the, the background color, the fill
color is specified by using the bg
argument.
So.
You, so, you can specify two different
colors like that if you want.
Here's another chart of the plotting
symbols and you can continue through the
demo here for points if you want and let
me just finish it up here.
It's just some of the special symbols that
you can plot if you want.
This is in a different font.
And let me just quit out of here.
So, so, that's one way to change the
symbol here.
I'm going to go back to my plot here, so
pch equals let's say, twenty.
Excuse me I have to regenerate my data
because it was overwritten by the example.
So, here is my data again my little
scatter plot.
Now, I can add a title to the plot by
using the title and I will say this is my
scatter plot and that adds the title.
I could add some text if I wanted to.
So, for example, I could use the text
function to say, add a little label here.
Let's say, I will give it the coordinates,
let's say -two and -two.
See that label appears there, I can add a
legend if I wanted to.
Save the legend, and the legend you can
give it kind of location specifications,
for example, top left will put the legend
in the top left, and then I'll say just
give it a specific label.
Excuse me, let me just put [unknown].
So now, I've got a little legend there.
And so there's all kinds of annotations
that you can add to the data as you kind
of go along.
So, for example, I could fiddle, if I want
to plot a line in the data, I can fit a
linear model using the lm function and
then the ab line function will add the
linear model fit on top of that here.
The data are related to the other, each
other so, that the linear model is, the
line is pretty flat.
If I wanted to adjust the thick, the
thickness of that line, I could use the ab
line and specify the lwd to be, let's say,
three.
You can see that a new line is plotted
over there, which is much thicker.
So, you probably wouldn't want to do this
or from the get-go, if you want to remake
this plot, you'd probably just specify
from the get-go lwd = three.
You don't want to just like plot two lines
on top of each other, but I'm just showing
this for demonstrate, demonstration sake.
I could have also changed the color.
So I make the color, say, blue and that
would make it blue.
And so there are lots of different types
of options you can specify here when
you're, as you're making a plot.
So, usually, you're going to, want to
create x labels and y labels which are,
kind of represent what the data are.
So, you can plot, you can put a lot of
these options in the plot function itself.
So, I could say, plot xy and maybe, and
maybe x lab is let's see, weight, and then
a y lay up a y lab will be, say, height.
Main will be scatter plot.
Pch will be twenty.
So, that gets, now I have actual labels on
the x-axis and y-axis.
I can put my legend back, if I want.
You know, I'll put it in the top right
this time.
And then I can add my little line here.
So, let's say, fit is, or maybe I'll make
the line red this time.
So, that's my plot with the labels with
the linear aggression line and with the
legend.
Now, lets see what happens when we try to
put more than one plot on the page.
So, for example, let's say, I have an
another variable which I'll call z.
And may be it's I don't know, let me make
some plus on data here.
Oh, excuse me.
And let's say, I want to plot z versus x
and then I also want to plot y versus x on
the same canvas here.
So the first thing I can do is, let's say,
I want to put, let's say, I want to put
the plots right on top of each other.
So, I'll say par mf row equals so, what is
going to happen is I want to have two rows
of plots and then one column of plots,
right?
So, that's what we want to see.
So now, let's plot x and y on top and x
and z on the bottom.
So, x and y, pch goes twenty, so you see
that goes on that top.
And on the bottom here, all you have x and
z, say, equals nineteen and that goes on
the bottom.
So now, you can see that the margins are
little bit large here, probably larger
than we would want.
And you see that the, the margin that I,
that's specified here is that.
And so, we probably want to adjust the
size of the margin, now that we've kind of
rearranged the configuration of the plots.
So, we can maybe say something like par,
same r equals that.
Now, if I plot it again, they get a little
bit bigger.
Say, twenty again.
So that's how, now I put two plots on the
screen.
I could have done it the other way.
I could have said, instead of having them
top and bottom, I could have had them
right and left, by saying par mf row
equals, say, one, two.
Now I can plot like this like that.
So, I can see I made the margins a little
bit too small cuz I lost my y-axis label
here.
So, I'm able to say par, I'll go back to
four, four, two, two like this and make
the plots again.
So, you can see that when you rearrange
the plotting layout, you might want to
rearrange the, the, the canvas itself to
kind of remove some of the white space.
I won't do that for the moment just so I
can continue with the demo here.
But, for example, you can put four plots
on a page like, say, mar equals, sorry, I
meant mf row equals two, two, that means
two rows and two columns.
So, I can say plot x and y, now go in the
upper left.
You see that, now if we plot x and z, you
might wonder where is the next plot going
to go?
Well, because I specified mf row, the
plots are going to go across the rows.
So, the next plot is going to be in the
upper right and then the next plot is
going to be in the lower left so let me
say, a plot of z and x instead of x and z.
And then, the last plot is going to go in
the lower right here.
So, that, now, I've got four plots on a
page by specifying, specifying the mf row
option.
If I've specified mf col the same thing
would've happened, but the order in which
the plots occurred would've been
different.
So now, I can say, plot xy and that
appears on the same place but the next
plot now is going to appear on the lower
left.
And the next plot is going to be in the
upper right and the last plot is going to
be in the lower right.
So, that's the difference between mf row
and mf col.
The last option I'll talk about here is
the points function, just as a, just a
demonstration to how you can annotate a
plot by adding things to it.
So let me just reset the plot regions so
that I'm only doing one plot at a time
here.
Now suppose I generate some data and
suppose that the data consists of, say,
men and women, so there's two groups of
people here.
So I'm just going to generate some data
here, and maybe I'll give them a little
relationship so it's a little bit more
interesting.
And let's say I've got another variable
here which is the group and its going to
be half and half.
So, there's two groups and the 50 level,
50 iteration speech.
Let me just give them names, let's say
labels.
So, you got males and females in this
group of people here.
You can see that it's a factor variable of
two levels.
So, suppose I want to plot the data, if I
just plot the data x and y you can not
tell who are the males and who are
females, right, because, they all are the
same color, for example.
And so, suppose I want to plot the data
and plot and make males one color and
females another color.
So, how do I do that?
So, first thing you want to do, the basic
idea is you're going to set up the plot
region, but you are not going to plot any
of the data.
And then you're going to add the data by
gender, so you can maybe add the females
first, and then add the males.
And the idea is that each time you add the
data points, there will be other different
colors, or perhaps a different plotting
symbol or whatever.
So, let, first, let's set up the plotting
region.
So, I'm going to say, plot xy.
So, I'm going to pass at the data but I'm
going to, say, type equals n.
So this means, make the plot but don't
actually put the data in there.
So, you can see when I hii, when I execute
this function, everything happens just
like before.
The labels are put in, the, the tick marks
are put in the margins are specified,
everything is there, except for the data.
So, the only thing that's missing is the
data.
And so, what I'm going to do is I'm going
to add the data, add one group at a time.
So, let's say, I add the males first,
like, say, point x.
Then, I'm going to subset the vectors that
the g, I only take the points, where g is
equal to male, right?
So, that's a subset.
And then, I'm going to say y, and g is
equal to male.
So, this is only going to plot the, plot
the points where, where the values of g
variable equal to males.
I'm going to set, make that color green,
okay?
So now, you can see the points on the, on
the screen are green.
Those are, those represent the male points
only.
So I can do the same thing for the
females.
I can say, points x and then g is equal to
female and the yg is equal to female.
And let's say, I'll make these blue.
So now, you can see that there are blue
circles for the females and there's green
circles for the males.
And so, you can see the two groups
separately within the scatter plot.
And so, sub setting based on a grouping
variable is very common when a making
plots.
And the points function can used to kind
of add points sequentially by group so
that it can specify different types
properties for each group.
You can also, in, in addition to varying
the color, I could have changed the
plotting symbol, so I could have said pch
equal to, I'll say, nineteen.
So, this is a kind of solid circle here,
and that would have given me a solid blue
circle for the females, and an open green
circle for the males.
So, that's one way to, to separate up
groups of data points on a single scatter
plot.