This lecture's going to be about plotting,
and it's going to provide, provide a brief
introduction to the, a few of the plotting
functions and mechanisms in R.
So, our first, this lecture's going to be
divided into two parts.
The, the first part I'm going to talk
about the base plotting paradigm, and in
the second part I'm going to talk about
the lattice plotting paradigm.
So, the basic idea with plotting in R is
that there are a couple of packages that
control the plotting engine and how things
work.
The main one, of course, is the graphics
package.
So, the graphics package, of course, comes
with R when you download it, and it's
usually loaded by default.
So, this contains many of the basic
functions for graphing including the plot
function, hist for histograms, boxplot for
boxplots, and many other kind of very
standard functions that you probably are
already familiar with.
The other major package for plotting is
the lattice package, and this code
contains code for producing what are
called trellis graphics.
And these are, this system is independent
of the base graphic system, so that the
plot has it's own functions like xyplot,
bwplot, level plot.
And they don't intersect at all with the
plot or the hist of the other functions in
the base graphic systems.
So, usually, you have to decide you, are
you going to use the great, the base
graphic system or the lattice graphic
system?
And, and for the most part, most people
will start with the base graphics so
that's what we'll start with here.
There's another package called grid, which
implements a lot of the kind of low-level
and kind of nitty gritty details that is,
that are used by the lattice package.
And, generally speaking, you're not going
to be calling functions from the grid
package directly, but rather this'll, this
package we'll be working behind the
scenes.
Finally, the GR devices package, which
stands for Graphics Devices, contains all
the code which implements the different
graphic devices that R can use.
Including the X11 device, the PDF device,
the postscript PNG, all kinds of things.
So, these are the things that you can
export graphics too, whether they be to a,
to the screen or, to some sort of file.
You will occasionally call these types of
functions directly, but for the most part,
this, the code is this pack is not,
generally speaking, for the user.
So, when you go, when you go to make a
plot in R, usually, there are a couple of
choices you have to think about.
Maybe not consciously, but sometimes,
consciously.
So, The first is, what device are you
going to use to make the plot?
So, when you call a, a base plotting
function in R, like plot, or hist, or
boxplot, and there isn't already a plot
window open.
What will usually happen is that a plot
window will open on your, on your computer
and the plot will appear in that window.
So, all the, and this is so that the
window that in which the plot appears is
called a plotting device.
And, depending on what type of platform
you're using, there's a different name for
that plotting device.
On Unix it's called X11, on Windows the
device is called Windows, and on Mac OS X
it's called Quartz.
So, for each one of these platforms,
there's a function corresponding to X11,
Windows, and Quartz which launches the
plotting window.
So, you have to think about first, where
do you want the plot to be sent?
Do you want it to be sent to the screen?
Do you want it to be sent to a file so
that you can include it somewhere else?
These are so, just, these, and cuz there
are different types of functions that you
can use to, for, for those different types
of operations.
The other question that's related is, you
know, what do you want to use to plot for?
Do you want to just show it on the screen
to see, to look at some data, maybe
temporarily?
Or, is this plot going to end up in a
paper?
So, it's going to be like a publication
type of thing?
Are you going to use it in a presentation?
So, like a PowerPoint slide or, you know,
like an overhead type of projector?
And so, these kinds of considerations will
defect, will affect a little bit the types
of things that you put into your plot.
For example, if you're going to be in a
presentation type of setting where there's
going to be people sitting, you know, 200
feet away, you probably don't want to have
very tiny little fonts with lots of little
dots and things like that because they
won't be visible from a long distance.
You're going to want to use bigger fonts,
bigger plotting symbols and things like
that.
Of course, if you're, if you're making a
plot for a paper, then you can have lots,
a lot more fine detail because, you know,
people will be looking at much closer
range.
And you can have all kinds of other kinda
richer details in that kind of a plot.
So, thinking about what, who the audience
is going to be, where the plot is going to
be presented, or key question for, you
know, how you're going to make the plot?
So, another question that's important is
that, is whether or not there's going to
be a large amount of data that goes into
the plot.
If you're going to have lots of points,
for example, if you're going to have
thousands and thousands or maybe millions
of points going into the plot then, that
will help determine what type of plotting
device you're going to use when you export
the plot to either the screen or to a
file.
If it was just going to be handful points,
may be ten or fifteen, then, then this is
usually not an important consideration.
And the last one is, whether or not you
need, you're going to be needing, able to
need to re-size the graphics.
Or, do you want your graph to be set at a
specific resolution, or do you, or you're
going to want to make it kind of larger
and smaller without compromising the
quality?
Usually, this will determine whether or
not you need a, you use a vector format
like a PDF or post script, or a bit map
format like JPEG or PNG.
The next question you're going to want to
ask yourself when making a plot is what
type, what graphics system are you going
to use?
The base graphics system or the grid slash
lattice system?
Generally speaking, you can't mix these
two systems so you're going to have to
kinda choose one set of functions over
another, another set of functions.
So, we're going to talk about the base
graphics system first.
And, the basic philosophy of the base
graphic systems is that it, you know, you
kind of construct a plot piecemeal.
So, the idea is that you kind of set up
the plotting region, and then you can
annotate the plot using different sets of
functions that will add to the plot.
And, and then as you can see, for example,
you can maybe put some points on a, on the
canvas.
You can draw a title.
You can add some access labels.
You can maybe annotate some of the points
in the plot, or, and add some color and
things like that.
Add a legend.
And this is all done one by one by a
different function calls.
And so, usually the process of making a
plot involves a long series of functions
where you kind of add things one by one.
Many people find this conceptually a
simpler process and often allows the kind,
the construction of the plot to mirror the
thought process.
So, you might be thinking, okay, I want to
put this points on the screen and then oh,
I want to add this label, and then oh, I
want to change the color here.
And so, it kind of mirrors the thought
process a little bit.
On the other hand, the lattice and the
grid graphic system, the way that you make
plots using the lattice package typically
is via a single function call.
And so, the idea is you kind of throw all
the details into a detailed function, and,
and then R makes the entire plot at once.
So, there's no adding of this and adding
of that.
And so, in some sense, you kinda have to
think of everything in advanced.
So, you, so, so you can put them all into
the single function.
So, if you're going to make a scatter plot
via the xyplot function.
The xyplot function has a large number of
options that you can specify to kind of
specify to kind of set the, the axis
labels, the colors, and the, and the
types, and, and the, to the plotting
symbol and things like that.
So, this is the kind of thing that, that
makes it a little bit different from the
base package The base graphic system
because, a plot will generally consists of
single function call rather than series of
function calls.
The advantage of using the lattice
approach is that R can automatically
calculate all the spacings, the margins,
the font sizes etc., so that everything
kind of looks nice from gecko, rather than
you have to kind of manually calculate
that as you go.
So, let's talk about the base graphic
system.
The base graphic system is, is a very
powerful tool for creating two dimensional
graphics.
And, for the most part, when I talk about
two dimensional graphics in this lecture.
And the most fundamental function is the
plot function.
And usually, you call plot with two
arguments, a vector x and a, and a vector
y.
So, the x, obviously the x vector
specifies the x coordinates for the two
dimensional plot, and the y vector
specifies the y coordinates.
Another function, of course, is something
like hist, which only takes a single
argument and it produces a histogram
showing the distribution of that numeric
vector, x.
Both of these functions will launch a
graphics device if one is not already
open.
So, typically, when you start up R, you're
not going to have a graphics device open.
So, the first time you call plot, it will
launch and you will see a graphics window
open.
And then, after it launches the graphics
window, it will draw the plot on the
device.
So, if the arguments to plot are not of
some special class.
So, if you're just going to give it, if
you're just passing it in some numeric
vector or of some sort, then the default
plotting method is called.
And the default plotting method has many
arguments because it lets you thing, set
things like the title, the x-axis labels,
the y-axis labels, etc.
And, you can specify these arguments if
you wish, or you can just use the default.
So, the base graphic system has many, many
other parameters too which are not
necessarily arguments to the default
plotting function.
And, all of these arguments can be set,
and tweaked, and modified, etc.
And so, and, and, and you're going to have
to know at least some of them so to, Tto
know how to customize your plots.
Most of the parameters are documented in
the help page for the par function.
So, the par function controls all the
graphing parameters.
And, as, you know, as I say here, it
wouldn't help to memorize this help page
if you're going to be doing a lot of
plotting.
So, the par function is used to specify
global graphics parameters that, so
anything that you set in the par function
will affect all plots that you make in a
single R session.
So, if you specify options to, to the plot
function, that will affect that plot but
won't affect, say, the next plot if you
specify the next option.
But anything that you set using the par
function will set, will affect the all of
the plots that you make.
So, this is, so, sometimes this is useful
to save yourself time to specify an option
every single time when you call a plot.
However, any option that is specified
using the par function can be overridden
by specifying it in the plot functions for
a specific plot.
So, a couple of very important options
that you should, definitely have memorized
are the pch option, which controls the
plotting character or the plotting symbol.
The default is an open circle but you can,
there are many, many options that you can
choose from here.
Lty is the line type.
So if you, if you plot a, if you make a
plot that has lines in it, for example,
like the time series plot or something
like that, it, it specifies what type of
line is going to be drawn, and the default
of course is the solid line.
But you can have a dash line, a dotted
line, a dash-dotted line, etc.
Lwd is the line width, so it controls the
thickness of the line that's drawn.
Col is the plotting color.
And, this determines what color the
plotting symbol, which default is the open
circle, will be plotted in the default.
Of course, it's going to be black.
Las is another nice option which precisely
orientation of the axis labels on the
plot.
Couple more options here, bg is the
background color for the canvas.
The default's going to be no background
color.
Mar is the margin size and this specifies
the margin around the plot so that there's
four sides of, of the, of the, of the
plotting region and you can have a
different size margin for each side.
Oma is the outer margin size, which is
the, kind of, the outside region of the
plot window.
And then the, two important options for
setting the number of plots on the canvas
which is mfrow, mfcol which can be set
separately.
They specify the number of plots per row
and column.
So, for example, it's, it's, if, if you
want to have, if you want to have more
than one plot, so you can have two plots,
or four plots and things like on the
canvas, you can set the mfrow and the
mfcol options.
The, the only difference between the two
is that when you specify mfrow, the plots
are filled in row-wise across the canvas.
And, when you specify mfcol, the plots are
filled in column-wise kind of down the
canvas.
So, you can look at the default values
that are specified for the various par
options.
So, for example, the default for lty is,
is solid.
So, this is a solid line.
The default for lwd is one, so one is the,
is kind of the standard thickness as you
increase the number.
So, if you go to two, three, four, the
thickness increases.
So, you can kind of adjust and you can use
this on a numeric scale so you can, so you
can have an lwd of 1.5 if you want or,
and, and that will be somewhere in between
one and two.
The default color for the plotting is
black, and the default pch is one which is
the open circle.
For the, for bg, you have a transparent.
S, this means that the canvas does not
have any color on the background.
You can specify a background color if you
want, but this is, in my experience,
fairly uncommon.
The mar option specifies, again, the
margins.
And, and the way this works is that there
are four numbers, and each number
represents the size of the margin for a
different side of the plotting region.
So, there's, there's four sides to the
square plotting region.
So, the, the, and you can think of it as
going clockwise around the plotting
region, starting around the, starting at
the very bottom.
So the, you get the x-axis at the, that's
the first side, the y-axis is the second
side.
The top of the plot is the third side and
the right side is the fourth side.
So, so you can see that the, the, the bot,
the x-axis, the bottom of the plot has the
largest amount of space, it has a 5.1.
The, the y-axis has the, has 4.1 for, for
amount of space.
The top of the plot has 4.1 and the, and
the right side has 2.1.
So, the right side of the plot has the
least amount of space.
And you can adjust these numbers if you
want to make more space or less space for
each side of the plot.
But, , the mar option is always a vector
of four numbers so one number per side.
The outer margin is, is a region that's
just outside of the margin.
And, again, there's four sides to this.
And so, the default the outer margin is
going to be zero.
The outer margin is really only relevant
if you have more than one plot per canvas.
So, if you only have a single plot, you
generally, not going to be using the outer
margin.
But, if you have many different plots,
then you want, sometimes you want to have
a label or a, or a, or something like that
for, that rep, that is relevant to all the
plots, not just a single plot.
Mfrow and mfcol are described before, the
defaults are one, one.
So, that's one plot per row, one plot per
column.
And so, that's of course, that just means
a single plot.
You can have, if you want to specify say,
four plots, you want to have like two by
two, then you have two plots per row, two
plots per column then that kind of has,
it's a four square type of thing.
If you wanted to have four plots for all
in a single row, then you could specify
mfrow would be one and then four, so it
would be one row, four columns, things
like that.
So, a couple of importing base, important
base plotting functions.
Of course, plot is a, is the probably the
most basic makes a scatter plot.
It may make another type of plot depending
on the class of the object being plotted.
So, if you have an object that's a, that
has a special class, that's not a numeric
vector or it's not an integer vector or
something like that, then plot may make a
different type of, of plot.
But, for the most part, we're going to be
making scatter plots with this function.
Lines is a function that adds.
So, so the following functions, sorry, is
going to, are going to add to a plot.
They're not going to make a plot by
themselves.
So, so functions like lines, points,
texts, etc., you cannot call them unless
you all, have already constructed a plot
on, on, on the plotting device.
So, lines adds lines to a plot.
So, basically, it plays connects the,
connect the dots.
So, if you give it a vector of x values
and vector of y values, it will put those,
it will put those points on the canvas and
connect the dots between them to create
lines.
Points, basically, adds points to a plot.
It's kind of like lines but it doesn't
actually draw the lines in between the
points, so you give it an x, a set of x
values and a set of y values and it puts
those points on the plot.
Text adds text labels to a plot.
So, you give it some coordinates and it
will, it will put the text at those
coordinates on the plot.
Title will add a title to the top of the
plot.
But, you can also use title to add things
like x-axis labels, y-axis labels, and
subtitles and things like that.
Mtext adds text to the margins, either the
inner margin or outer margin of the plot.
An axis adds, annotates the, the axes.
So, like things like the tick marks, you
can add special labels to the tick marks
if you don't want the defaults.
So, the diff, there are a number of
different types of graphics devices that
you can plot, send plots to besides the
screen.
So, the screen will just be whatever the
default is for your dev, platform, so on
X11 on Unix, Windows on Windows, and
Quartz on the Mac.
So, but there are other types of devices
that you might want to use.
Probably, the most common is the PDF
device.
And this is very nice for making kind of,
print quality graphics for line type
graphics.
It's a vector format, so it re-sizes very
well without losing any quality.
And it's, it's viewable on pretty much any
modern platform.
The PDF, so most, if you're using, if
you're making a scatter plot or that kind
of a thing, those, that's, that's a line
type graphic.
It's going to be suitable for PDF.
Postscript is an older format, kind of a
predecessor to PDF.
It's generally not used very often right
now and so I would recommend against using
it.
Xfig is a format that's specifically for
Unix, and it's useful if you want to edit
the plot by hand, but it's not
particularly common.
So, bitmap formats are very important for,
for, for graphics that are things like
imagines.
Or, if you are going to make a graphic
that has lots and lots of points on it,
typically you're going to want to use a
bitmap format because it reduces the size
of the graphics file.
So, for example, if you have a plot, if
you have a scatter plot that has, you
know, two million points on it.
If you make a PDF file of that, the PDF
document has to specify kind of, a little
bit information for every single one of
those points.
So, two million points may be two things
and it, and the PDF file's going to be
very, very large if you make a PDF version
of that graphic.
However, a bitmap device, sorry, a bitmap
format will always be the same.
It will, will just specify as a number of
pixels and so you don't have to specify
information for every single object in the
plot.
And so, and furthermore, most of the
bitmap formats are, are compressed and,
and so the size, the file sizes tend to be
a lot smaller.
So, if, so if the file size is important
to you, then you're going to want to learn
about bitmap formats.
The disadvantage of bitmap formats is that
they generally, they generally don't
re-size very well.
So, if you try to re-size them, then
you'll lose some quality.
And so, they generally, they're designed
to be of a specific size for their, for
specific resolution and, and they don't
re-size very well.
So, PNG is a very nice format.
It's good for line drawings, images with
solid colors, surface things like scatter
plots, and, and it uses a lossless
compression algorithm.
For those of you who are a little bit
older, you might remember the old GIF
format.
So, it's kind of like the old GIF format.
But, and in most web browsers these days
can read this format natively, so you
don't have to worry about it being, not
being able to be read in a web browser.
The JPG format, most of you are probably
familiar with, is good for photographs or
natural scenes.
It uses lossy compression, and so you'll
lose some quality.
But the file size tends to be very, very
small.
If you use, if you use JPG for line
drawings, you'll probably see a little bit
of distortion.
So, it's not particularly good for that.
Again, it doesn't re-size particularly
well because it's a bitmap format and,
but, of course, any would, any computer,
any web browser can read a JPG file these
days.
Bitmap is a function that's used to create
bitmap files in certain, in certain, in
situations where you cannot use the PNG
and JPG functions.
These are rare, they usually involve
situations where you're running R in the
batch mode.
And, so you can't call those other
functions.
But, and so, this can be used to create in
a variety of bitmap formats.
But, generally you won't, you will not
need to use it in most situations, for
example, if you're running it, R on your
laptop.
Finally, the BMP format is a native
Windows bitmap format.
It's usually used for specifying things
like icons.
So, when you make the, when you make a
plot, there's kind of two basic
approaches.
First, is you, if you want to send a plot
to a file, you can either, you can first
approach to launch a graphics device, make
the plot, add things to it, annotate it if
you need it, then close the graphics
device.
The other process is you can make a plot
on a screen, annotate if needed, and then
you can copy the plot to another device.
For example, you can copy the plot to
another screen device, so another window,
or you can copy the plot to a file.
So, copying the plot to another device can
be useful because if you, if you recall a
lot of different functions for making the
plot, it can be kind of a pain to type all
that code again if you just want to see
the plot on different device.
So, for example, if you want to save the
plot to a file, usually the easiest thing
to do is to say, dev.copy2pdf which will
copy a plot to a PDF file.
And then, you can have a, a PDF version of
that file, of that plot, excuse me, and
then you can include that in a paper,
include that in a presentation, etc.
Of course, it's always good to save the
code that you used to make a plot, because
if you ever close R and then start up
again and you wanted to make that plot
again, you're going to want to have that
code lying around rather, rather than have
to kind of, rethink how you made that plot
over again.
So, always save the code for making a plot
so that you can reproduce it at a later
date.
Some basic functions, though, for copying
of plots are dev.copy, which just copies
from one device to another device.
Dev.copy2pdf, I mentioned already, copies
from one device, usually the screen, to a
PDF file.
Dev.list shows how many open graphics
devices there are.
Dev.next will switch control to another
graphics device cuz you can only plot to a
single graphics device at a time.
Dev.set will determine, can let, can let
you set which graphics device you're
plotting on, and dev.off will close the
current graphics device.
So, copy, copying plots is not an exact
operation.
So, if you have a plot that's on your
screen, and you copy it to a PDF file, it
may not be exactly what you see on the
screen just because there's some
approximation that has to occur when you
copy plots from one device to another.